Well, I reckon you're here because you
want to learn how to compare the
similarities and differences of the four
regions of the British colonies in North
America. And wouldn't you know it,
that's exactly what I want to talk
about. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it. All
right. Now, I can see you're positively
stoked to jump right into the
comparison, but put your patient pants
on because I need to set the stage first
so you can understand what this is all
about. Now, as I mentioned in the last
video, Great Britain, although they were
a little late to the New World
imperialization game, they got busy
colonizing North America in the 17th
century. And by the end of this time
period, which is 1754, there were 13
distinct British colonies on the eastern
coast of North America and a cluster of
colonies down here in the Caribbean
known as the British West Indies. Oh, by
the way, if you want know guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
including quizzes to help you remember
it all, then there's a link down below.
Anyway, the thing to remember here is
that most of the people who migrated to
these colonies from Great Britain were,
you know, like British. They spoke
English. They were generally Protestant
Christians. They got all giddy when
thinking about a limited monarchy as
laid out by the dang Magna Carta. They
loved Mr. Bean movies. You get the idea.
Anyway, by the end of this period, four
distinct regions had developed
throughout the British colonial
territory. And while they did have some
similarities, there were a metric
buttload of differences. So, the
question that we're about to answer in
this video is how in the fresh heck did
each of these regions develop such
unique cultures and societies? And that
is a fine question, my dear people. So,
let's get the party started in New
England. Okay, to be clear, I'm going to
walk through these regions
geographically from north to south.
Actually, that is not the chronological
order in which the colonies were
founded. Well, that's true, me from back
there. But why don't you drink a tall
glass of shut the heck up and let me
explain. So we could go chronologically
but I think the spatial comparison is
easier to remember and that's why I want
to do it this way. Okay, so this region
right here is called New England and by
the end of the period it would include
these five colonies. Now the first
colony established was the Plymouth
settlement in 1620 which we talked about
in the last video. But by way of
reminder, Plymouth was settled by a
group of separatists, otherwise known as
the pilgrims who left Great Britain in
search of religious freedom and economic
opportunity. And one of the big things
to remember about these folks is that
they mainly migrated as whole family
groups. And that means they came in
order to create a whole dang society.
And as it turned out, they wanted that
society to operate strictly according to
the principles of the Christian Bible.
In other words, church and state were in
no way separated. The church was the
state and the state was the church. It
was the starch. Anyway, before they left
their ship, they drew up and signed the
Mayflower Compact, which was an
agreement to form a simple government
that ruled by the will of the majority,
which was an unusually democratic style
of governance for the time. Now, to be
clear, this document was not a
constitution, but it did create the
conditions for self-government in the
new colony, even though only the more
elite adult males could participate.
Now, because their goal was to establish
a whole society, the pilgrims adopted
agriculture as their way of life. Now,
the first year they starved real bad and
many of them died, not least because
they were suspicious of the indigenous
people at their borders. However,
eventually they accepted help from the
indigenous people who taught them some
local agricultural techniques. And after
that, they experienced much better
harvest. And so after they figured out
how to live with the land and support
themselves, the Plymouth settlers
eventually developed a modest economy
based on the export of lumber and beaver
pelts and fish. Okay. Now, the second
major New England colony you need to
know was the Massachusetts Bay Colony.
It was established in 1630 by a group of
about a thousand Puritan settlers. And
just like Plymouth, it was settled by
family groups and organized its
government and society according to the
Bible with Jesus running the show. And
you couldn't get a clearer statement of
purpose for this colony than a sermon
from its first governor, John Winthro.
He said that the Massachusetts colony
would be as a city upon a hill, which is
to say, everybody could look at this
colony and it would be so godly and so
perfect that they could use it as a
template to run their own crap. Now, in
this colony, all freemen who owned
property could vote on policy matters. A
far larger proportion of eligible voters
than existed in England. And like in
Plymouth, they debated their policies in
town hall meetings in the will of the
majority carried the day. Now, to be
clear, not just any regular schmo could
be considered a freeman, but only those
who held to a strict Puritan ideology.
Anyway, in time, the Massachusetts
colony merged with Plymouth to become a
massive Puritan colonial party. But
here's where I tell you that not
everybody at the party was stoked about
the religious intolerance that
characterized the Puritan settlements.
It's hard to believe, I know, but some
people actually found themselves
disagreeing with the strictctures of
Puritan authority. And I'm in the mood
to give you two examples. First, meet
our boy Roger Williams. Now, he himself
was a Puritan minister in Massachusetts,
but he started thinking that the
complete merger of church and state was
a pretty dumb idea. He also thought that
religious toleration was much more
befitting a society of God than
religious intoleration. And as a reward
for such blasphemous beliefs, he was
banished from Massachusetts and founded
what would later become the Rhode Island
colony, which became a haven for
religious denters. And that reminds me
of a second denter you should know,
namely Anne Hutchinson, who was all
kinds of spicy. First of all, she was a
woman in a society that declared men to
be spiritually superior. Second, she
developed the belief that everyone had
equal access to inspiration from the
Holy Spirit, including women. I know.
Anyway, she went around teaching these
things and taking a metaphorical dump on
the tight religious conformity of
Puritan society. So, the Puritan
authorities went ahead and banished her
from the colony. So, she set up shop in
what would soon become the Rhode Island
colony on Roger Williams invitation.
Okay, so just to sum up, society in the
New England region was characterized by
several factors. First, the social
fabric of the region was deeply
religious. Second, the geography
included rocky soil and harsh winters,
which meant that they could only engage
in limited agriculture. Third, because
many of these migrants arrived in family
groups, they created tight-knit towns
centered around the church. And fourth,
their economy majored in exporting goods
like fish and lumber, all of which could
be found in abundance in this region.
And that commerce would eventually link
them economically to the other colonies
and then the wider transatlantic trade.
Okay, now let's move right along to the
middle colonies, which included New
York, New Jersey, Delaware, and
Pennsylvania. And just for poops and
giggles, let's start with New York. Now,
if you'll recall from a previous video,
this area was previously a Dutch colony
by the name of New Amsterdam. And the
Dutch were very much not interested in
all the we're a city on a hill and God's
beacon to all of humanity stuff going on
up north. The Dutch just wanted to make
money. And so New Amsterdam became a
thriving commercial seapport with all
kinds of different people from different
cultures living there. And the whole
reason I'm floapping my mouth hole about
all of that is because once the British
King Charles II decided to send the Duke
of York to York the colony out of Dutch
hands for the British, a lot of that
cultural and economic character stayed
with it. So New York became a thriving
trading colony on account of its
abundance of rivers and natural
seaports. And because their geography
included river valleys with rich soil,
unlike the New England colonies, New
York made buttloads of money by
exporting grain. That's why this whole
region became known as the bread basket.
Anyway, like the Dutch settlement before
it, New York became home to a diverse
group of European immigrants who arrived
seeking to better themselves
economically. Now, eventually the king
got a little saucy about the size of the
New York colony and so he divided it in
1664. And by 1702, that new section
became New Jersey, which was a royal
colony that shared many of the same
characteristics that I mentioned about
New York. And by the way, royal colony
just refers to a colony in which the
governor and the council were appointed
directly by the monarch. And then
another big deal colony in this region
was Pennsylvania, founded in 1681 by
William Penn. Now, Penn's ambitions for
creating this colony was different from
what we've seen so far. You see, Penn
was a Quaker. And Quakers, otherwise
known as the Society of Friends, were
especially targeted for religious
marginalization both in British and
colonial society. Why says you? Well
says I. Quakers emphasized individual
religious experience guided not so much
by the Bible or paid clergy but rather
by an inner light possessed equally by
everyone. Additionally, Quakers were
pacifists which means they refused
military service. And given their
emphasis on spiritual equality, they
refused to support Anglican clergy or
churches with their tax money. So Penn
decided to establish Pennsylvania as a
refuge for Quaker denters and all other
denters who felt the pressure for their
religious beliefs. And that conviction
shaped colonial society here. As
pacifists, Quakers in Pennsylvania
treated indigenous people with dignity,
emphasizing equitable diplomacy in their
dealings. Also, freedom of worship was
guaranteed to all colonists who lived in
Pennsylvania. Although, to be fair, the
British government did force Penn to
deny opportunities for holding office
from Jews and Catholics. But, you know,
that was not Penn's decision. And so,
compared to the other British colonies,
Pennsylvania was unusually democratic
since policy decisions were made by an
elected representative assembly who were
chosen by land owners. And given
Pennsylvania's non-discriminatory
practices, the colony attracted a very
diverse population. And in that
environment, Pennsylvania's economic
sector grew rapidly, particularly in the
export of grain and other crops, which
is similar to the other middle colonies.
And so now, let's sum up what you know
about this region. First, the soil was
deep and fertile, which meant that
agriculture was a booming business in
this region. Second, the population was
way more diverse than any of the other
regions because of the emphasis on
religious tolerance and economic
opportunity. Third, in terms of
governance, the middle colonies tended
to be less participatory than the town
hall meetings in New England, but more
participatory than what we're going to
find in the South. Speaking of which,
let's move right on down and talk about
the Chesapeake and North Carolina
region. Now, if we had been doing all of
this chronologically, this is where we
would have started because Jamestown was
Britain's first colony established over
here in6007. Now, the main goal of the
settlers at Jamestown, which was within
the colony that would later become
Virginia, was profit. Which is to say,
they looked in their pockets and found
plenty of room room for some boom boom.
And so most of the migrants who showed
up here were single men as opposed to
the family groups that settled in New
England. And that should tell you that
they were not at all interested in
creating a society here. They just
wanted to smack the soil and make it
cough up all of its gold quick, fast,
and in a hurry. But unfortunately for
them, there wasn't much gold to be had
there. And since they didn't much bother
to plant crops to feed themselves, many
of those first settlers starved to
death. In fact, it got so bad that some
of the settlers turned to cannibalism to
survive. Is this Jerry? This tastes like
Jerry. Is it too soon to make 17th
century cannibalism jokes? I don't know.
Anyway, the colony definitely turned
around once John Ralph came in and
created the conditions for prosperity in
Virginia by leading the colonist to
plant and harvest tobacco, which created
an insatiable demand in Great Britain.
And while that development was great for
the wealth of the colony, it also
created some problems. You see, tobacco
planting is real hard on the soil. And
so, as they planted it year after year,
the soil kind of shriveled up like an
old monkeykey's kneecap. But since the
demand for tobacco was still high, that
meant that these settlers needed more
land on which to plant. Now, that would
cause some conflicts with the indigenous
people living in the region, but we'll
get to that in another video. Anyway,
because tobacco became the most
important export of Virginia, it led to
the development of sprawling
plantationstyle plots, which was the
chief characteristic of Chesapeake
colonies, which were far more
agricultural compared to northern
regions. Now, at first, most of the
labor was completed by indentured
servants. But in 1619, a Dutch ship
entered the Virginia Harbor and sold
about 20 African indentured servants to
the planters. And then gradually,
African slavery would replace indentured
servitude as the main labor system in
these colonies. And as for governance,
again, it was unusually democratic for
the time period. Here they established
the House of Burgesses, which acted as a
representative government. And this body
would inspire later forms of
self-government in the colonies as well,
even though participation was restricted
to property white men. Now, North
Carolina was established as a royal
colony in 1712. But for our purposes,
most of what I said about Virginia can
also be applied to this colony as well.
So, I'll save your brain the effort. And
that means it's time to sum up the
characteristics of this region. First,
the warmer weather meant that large
sprawling plantations became the
defining feature of the landscape. ape
and they majored in the export of
tobacco. Second, the need for more land
to plant crops led to westward expansion
and conflict with indigenous peoples.
Third, while the House of Burgesses
represented a step toward democratic
institutions, over time, politics was
ruled by a small cadre of elite
planters. And fourth, by the end of the
period, the dominant source of labor
here was enslaved African workers. Okay.
And finally, let's head all the way down
to the south and see what's going on in
those colonies. And first, let's go to
the British West Indies because what's
happening there will inform what's
happening back on the mainland. So by
far the highest concentration of
enslaved labor in the British colonies
was found in the British West Indies. So
thanks to its proximity to the equator,
these islands enjoyed long warm growing
seasons. And it quickly became apparent
that the most profitable crop to grow
here would be sugarce. And like the
Chesapeake region, the geography of the
BWI became defined by these massive and
sprawling plantations. And so as demand
for sugar spiked throughout Europe, that
created the need for more laborers to
grow and process it. And then that in
turn created a massive demand for
enslaved laborers from Africa. And it
wouldn't be long before enslaved
Africans outnumbered the white colonists
nearly 4 to1. So that means society in
the British West Indies was wholesale
shaped by plantation agriculture and an
abundance of slave labor. But it appears
that while their heads agreed with that
logic, their guts were a little more
wobbly because being thus outnumbered by
black people got them all kinds of
fearful and paranoia. And so to quench
that fear and paranoia, they passed the
Barbados slave codes, which was a series
of laws that stripped all rights from
black workers and granted white planters
complete power over them. And that, as
you might imagine, led to brutal and
vicious treatment of enslaved laborers
in order to keep them in their place,
which I guess was the white people's
best idea for decreasing black
resentment against their white
overlords. So, you know, it whatever.
It's not going to last forever. Anyway,
I wanted to start with the BWI because
now as we move up to South Carolina,
we're going to see a lot of overlap. So,
this colony was separated from North
Carolina in 1712 and was established as
a royal colony. However, long before
this, the colony specialized
economically in the fur trade and
providing food for the population of the
West Indies. And why didn't they grow
their own food in the West Indies? Well,
because there wasn't any room on account
of all those sugar cane plantations. But
it wasn't long before planters from the
West Indies started showing up in South
Carolina and bringing their slave codes
with them. And in doing so, South
Carolina was gradually transformed into
a kind of mirror image of the West
Indies, except instead of majoring in
sugarcane, they focused on growing rice
and indigo. And since their growing
number of African slaves had experience
in rice cultivation, the system of
slavery became entrenched in their
society. However, it's going to be
important to know that these enslaved
Africans fought to preserve their own
cultural and religious autonomy in
opposition to all the efforts of
planters to dehumanize them. For
example, many West African slaves
refused to accept the Christianity of
their white masters, but instead
synretized Christianity with many
aspects of their native West African
belief system, Vodun. And one way they
did this was by associating traditional
Christian saints with Vodun spirits. And
in that way, African slaves were able to
maintain their cultural heritage while
giving birth to a new blended belief
system. Anyway, in South Carolina, these
strict slave codes quickly created a
rigid social hierarchy in which a few
wealthy planters were on the top and
then common white planters were in the
middle and then the dominant black
population was on the bottom. And as
such, these elite planters with their
massive tracks of land dominated the
affairs of local politics. Now, Georgia
is also in this region, but it won't be
till next period that it really starts
to resemble its regional partners. I
mean, it was just kind of established as
a prison colony for British debtors. and
more importantly as a protective buffer
between Spanish Florida and the wildly
profitable Carolinas. And so let's sum
up the southern colonies. First, the
southern colonies were dominated by
large plantationstyle agriculture with
massive populations of enslaved
Africans. Second, the need to control
the enslaved population led to the
imposition of a rigid social hierarchy
enforced by an elaborate system of race
laws. Third, politics in the southern
colonies was restricted mainly to
decisions made by a small group of elite
planters who wielded the most power. All
right, well done on getting through that
one. You can click right here to watch
my other videos for unit two. And you
can click here to grab my video note
guides which are going to help you get
all the content of this course firmly
crammed into your brain folds. I
appreciate you coming around and I'll
catch you on the flipflop.